Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund Records, 1969-2012
Sophia Smith Collection
Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund records
1969-2012
Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund
354
82 boxes (32.5 linear feet)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
International organization. Records of officers, Board of Trustees and directors, and annual meetings make up approximately half of the collection. Correspondence and memoranda are extensive. The other half consists of files of various committees, including the Project Grants Committee, whose members screen grant applications and semi-annually recommend the most promising ones to the Board of Trustees and directors for funding. Records of the Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund (VGIF) sponsorship of the International Federation of University Women and of the Asian Women's Institute are particularly strong, and other project grants are well-documented.
Originally called the Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund for University Women, the Virginia Gildersleeve Inernational Fund (VGIF) was founded in 1969 by a group of women affiliated with the International Federation of University Women. They sought to create a fund to provide monies for projects "which further the development of educational theory and practice, foster the development of human resources, and advance the cause of mutual understanding and cooperation among university women throughout the world," particularly in developing nations. The incorporators named the fund for Virginia Gildersleeve, Dean of Barnard College from 1911 to 1947, in honor of her commitment to the concept that women college graduates could, given the resources, make significant contributions to the development of their countries and to the world at large. To this end, the organization regularly underwrites conferences, workshops, and educational projects undertaken by individuals and organizations all over the world. Funded projects typically included conferences on international women's issues, small-scale economic schemes, micro-credit loans, educational activities, environmental endeavors, sex education and HIV-related projects. In 1997, the VGIF achieved NGO status at the United Nations.
For a comprehensive history of the Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund, please see History: 1968-1978, by former president Althea K. Hottel in SERIES I: ADMINISTRATION.
The Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund Records consist of 32.5 linear feet of materials dating from 1969 to 2011. Because VGIF officers have requested that additions to the records be processed periodically, the container list consists of three parts. Though there is some overlap of dates in all three parts, materials in Part I (8.5 linear feet) document the years 1969 to 1996, the bulk of the materials in Part II (9.5 linear feet) cover the years 1993 to 2001, and Part III (14.5 linear feet) primarily documents the years 2000 to 2011. More records will be added when they are no longer in current use by the organization. Parts I, II and III are each arranged in three series:
I. ADMINISTRATION
II. COMMITTEES
III. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS AND COMPUTER MEDIA
Approximately one third of the collection is comprised of files of the Officers, the Board of Trustees/Directors, and the Annual Meetings of the general membership. The administrative files are for the most part complete and span the organization's entire history, with some exceptions: the records of the Secretary cover only 1972 to 1978 and 1993 to 1996, and the years 1985 and 1986 are missing from the files of the Board of Directors/Trustees. The correspondence and memoranda are extensive, and reveal much about the workings of the Officers and the Board with regard to the purpose and function of the organization.
The rest of the collection consists of the files of various committees, particularly those of the Project Grants Committee, whose members screen grant applications and recommend, semi-annually, the most promising ones to the Board of Trustees/Directors for funding. Records of VGIF sponsorship of the International Federation of University Women and of the Asian Women's Institute are particularly strong, and other project grants are also well documented. For a concise overview of the history of VGIF (UW) committees, see "Final Report of VGIF Task Force on Organizational Structure, 2007" in Box 57, Folder 16.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection. However, researchers wishing to view VGIF records must agree, in writing, not to use personal identifiers until 25 years from date of creation of the document. In addition, VGIF requests that a log be kept of permissions asked and granted, and that it be shared with the organization.
Accruals are donated by VGIF periodically. Newer additions may not be reflected in this record.
The officers of the corporation began donating the records of the Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund in 1989, and have continued to add to them on a regular basis.
American Association of University Women--History; Asian Women's Institute--History--Sources; Educational assistance--Developing countries; International Federation of University Women--History--Sources; League of Women Voters (U.S.)--History; Pan-Pacific relations--Societies, etc.; University cooperation; Virginia Gildersleeve International Fund--History--Sources; Women--Education (Higher)--History; Women in community development--Developing countries--History; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Women philanthropists--History--Sources; Women--Societies and clubs--History--Sources
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1960-2011
  This series contains general administrative records and those of the President, Secretary, Treasurer, Board of Trustees/Directors, and the Annual Meetings of the general members. Material pertaining to general administration is arranged alphabetically, and other records are listed in the order given above. Types of material include correspondence and memoranda, agendas and minutes, reports, financial information, proxies and ballots, and brochures and newsletters. In keeping with the original order of the records, the President's files are arranged by topic. Records of Annual Meetings consist mainly of agendas, minutes, and reports; additional materials pertaining to the meetings can also be found in the officers' records and in SERIES II. COMMITTEES. The Board of Trustees/Directors met annually in April from 1970 until sometime between 1984 and 1987, after which they met semi-annually in April and October or November. Records of the meetings of the Board are arranged chronologically.
  This series is comprised of three parts. Part I spans 1969-1994 and measures 4.5 linear feet. Part II spans 1972-2003, with the bulk of materials between 1993-2001, and measures 5 linear feet. Part III spans 1960-2011, with the bulk of materials between 2000-2011, and measures 3.5 linear feet.
- SERIES II. COMMITTEES 1970-2011
  This series consists of the records of the various committees formed as necessary to attend to specific VGIF business. Types of material include correspondence, memoranda, photographs, and reports. The committees are listed alphabetically, with the exception of the Project Grants Committee, which, due to the volume of material it generates, is listed last. Researchers may also wish to cross-reference material in this series with the records of the Officers and the Board of Trustees/Directors in SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION.
  Project Grants Committee material is comprised of general committee records and files on project proposals submitted for possible funding. Correspondence pertaining to a specific project is filed with that project; general correspondence and memoranda in which the project is mentioned along with other business may be found in the general correspondence of the Project Grants Committee. Grant files are arranged alphabetically by continent and subsequently by country in Parts I and II. Because VGIF significantly expanded the number of grants it awarded early in the 21st century, grant files in Part III are arranged by the year in which the grants were initially funded. In 1989, VGIF began assigning numbers to proposals; thus, grants from 1989 onward are filed by grant number. VGIF numbered all project proposals, but only retained files on projects that were funded, so the numbers that appear here are not sequential.
  Project Grant files typically include the application, correspondence, mid-year and final reports, sometimes a site visit report, sometimes photos, and on occasion promotional materials from the organization such as posters and flyers. Note that information on the International Federation of University Women (IFUW) can be found both in Project Grant files and in the administrative files, as VGIF both funded and participated in the triennial conference.
  Project grant files also document concerns about fraudulent projects (see Project #1683, #1850, #2056, #2130, #2514, #2556, #2854, and #3124), whether projects benefitted men more than women (see Project #1992 and Project #2056) and policies relating to subsequent funding of successful projects (see Project #1992 and Project #2417).
  Note on names: The Constitution and Bylaws Committee changed its name to the Governance Committee in the 2000s. After April 2008, the On-Site Visit Program became known as the Funded Grants Evaluation Committee.
  This series is comprised of three parts. Part I spans 1970-1996 and measures 4 linear feet. Part II spans 1984-2002 and measures 4.5 linear feet. Part III spans 1973-2011, with the bulk of materials between 1999-2009, and measures 10 linear feet.
- SERIES III. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS AND COMPUTER MEDIA
  This series includes CD-R, DVD-RW, audio cassette, and VHS files related to VGIF administration and project grants.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  - PART I.
    - Bequests, 1990-92 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Breakfast meetings given at American Association of University Women conventions, 1987, 1989, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1970-84 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - History: 1968-1978, by Althea K. Hottel, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lists of board and committee members, 1978-99 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Membership
      - 1970-90 (Box 1, Folder 7-13)
      - 1991-94 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
      - Australian Federation, 1987-93 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Potential consultants and cooperating organizations, 1974-75, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Proposed name change, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Public relations
      - VGIF brochure: correspondence and printed matter, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Articles about VGIF, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - VGIF newsletters, 1979-84 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Request for United Nations accreditation, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Officers
      - President
        - Correspondence
          - General
            - 1970-75 (Box 2, Folder 13-18)
            - 1976-94 (Box 3, Folder 1-13)
          - Board and general membership meetings
            - 1987-91 (Box 3, Folder 14-22)
            - 1992-93 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
          - VGIF Secretary, 1987-92 (Box 4, Folder 4-9)
          - VGIF Treasurer, 1987-93 (Box 4, Folder 10-16)
          - Project Grants Committee, 1987-93 (Box 4, Folder 17-21)
          - Development Committee, 1987-93 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
          - Global Network Committee, 1990-93 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
        - Public relations, 1987-91 (Box 5, Folder 6-9)
      - Secretary
        - Correspondence and reports, 1972-78 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
        - Financial records, 1973-78 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
      - Treasurer
        - Correspondence and reports, 1970-77, 1984-86 (Box 6, Folder 8)
        - Lists of contributions, 1969-72 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Board of Trustees/Directors
      - Minutes of the first meeting of the incorporators, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Executive committee/officers' meetings
        - Correspondence, agendas, minutes and reports, 1971-92 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
      - Board meetings
        - Correspondence, agendas, minutes, proxies, ballots attendance records and reports (Box 7)
          - 1970-76 (Box 7, Folder 4-15)
          - 1977-93 (Box 8, Folder 1-17)
    - Annual Meetings
      - Correspondence, agendas, minutes, reports, attendance records, proxies and ballots
        - 1969-72 (Box 8, Folder 18-21)
        - 1972-75 (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
        - 1975-77 (Box 10, Folder 1-10)
        - 1978-93 (Box 11, Folder 13-27)
  - PART II.
    - Sophia Smith Collection: Certificate of Gift and related correspondence, 1989-98 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence re: 9/11 attack, Sep-Oct 2001 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Endowments and gifts: correspondence and deeds, 1990-92, 2001-02 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Legal counsel: correspondence and memoranda, 1993-96 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Certificate of Incorporation and related documents, 1972, 1998 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Tax exemption documents, 1988-93 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Lease, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Web site development: printouts, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1978-93 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - History
      - Correspondence, articles, clippings, essay, and speech, 1985-95 (Box 24, Folder 10)
      - United Nations Preamble controversy: correspondence, articles, and clippings, 1995-96 (Box 24)
    - Lists of board and committee members, 1996-99 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Canadian Federation of University Women Conference re: VGIF attendance: emails and memoranda, 2000 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Annual reports, 1995-96 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Membership lists, 1979-84, 1987-98 (Box 24, Folder 15-17)
    - Public relations
      - Brochures, bookmarks, and business cards, 1993-97, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - CD and audiocassette sales: correspondence and memoranda, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - VGIF lapel pins: correspondence and memoranda, 1995-99 (Box 25, Folder 3)
      - Posters: correspondence, 1998 (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Newsletters, 1979-2001 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1993-95 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Planning for Change: A Handbook for Training Workshop Leaders in Organizational Development and Strategic Planning: manual, 1994 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - United Nations/NGO: applications, brochures, correspondence and memoranda, 1991-96, 2000-01 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - VGIF Book III: Minutes/Record Book, Nov 1984-May 1987 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Officers
      - President
        - Correspondence
          - General, 1993-2002 (Box 25, Folder 10)
          - Gift acknowledgements, 1996-97 (Box 26, Folder 1)
          - Executive Committee, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 2)
          - Board of Directors, 1993-2001 (Box 26, Folder 3)
          - Secretary, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 4)
          - Treasurer, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 5)
          - Membership Development Committee, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 6)
          - Project Grants Committee, 1994-96 (Box 26, Folder 7)
          - Committee appointments, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 8)
          - Australian Federation of University Women, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 9)
          - International Federation of University Women, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 10)
          - Iowa Peace Institute, 1993-94 (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - Reports, 1982-93 (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Secretary: correspondence, 1993-96 (Box 26, Folder 13)
      - Treasurer
        - Insurance policy: correspondence and contract, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 14)
        - Correspondence, 1997-2001 (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
        - Endowed fund reports
          - Asian Regional Endowment, 1997-2000 (Box 27, Folder 4)
          - Erna Hamburger Fund, 2000 (Box 27, Folder 5)
        - Reports, annual statements, and related correspondence, 1989-2000 (Box 27, Folder 6-10)
        - Financial information re: grants awarded by VGIF: correspondence, memoranda, and facsimiles
          [see also Series II: Committees: Project grants]
          - 1997 (Box 27, Folder 11)
          - 1999-2001 (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
        - Petty cash: memoranda and receipts, 1999-2001 (Box 28, Folder 4-6)
        - Expense accounts: forms, memoranda, and receipts, 1999-2001 (Box 28, Folder 7-9)
        - Investment reports: correspondence, proxies and statements, 1999-2002 (Box 29, Folder 1-3)
        - Bank statements and cancelled checks, 1999-2001 (Box 29, Folder 4-6)
        - Tax returns, 1986-95, 1997, 2000 (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
        - Donations: charts, forms, and deposit slips
          - 1997-Jun 1999 (Box 30, Folder 3-9)
          - Jul 1999-Aug 2000 (Box 31, Folder 1-19)
          - Sep 2000-Jun 2001 (Box 32, Folder 1-10)
          - Jul-Dec 2001 (Box 33, Folder 1-6)
        - Donation summaries, 2001-02 (Box 33, Folder 7)
        - Balance sheet and check stubs, 1992-2001 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Board of Trustees/Directors
      - Handbook, 2002 (Box 33, Folder 9)
      - Executive committee/officers' meetings
        - Correspondence, memoranda, agendas, minutes, and reports
          - 1993-2000 (Box 33, Folder 10-17)
          - 2001-02 (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
      - Board meetings: correspondence, agendas, minutes, and reports, 1994 - Apr 2002 (Box 34, Folder 3-17)
    - Annual meetings: correspondence, agendas, minutes, reports, attendance records, proxies and ballots, 1994-2002 (Box 35, Folder 1-9)
  - PART III.
    - Annual and mid-year meetings
      - Constitutional amendments, Board minutes, and correspondence: Elizabeth May to Althea Hottel, 1969 (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - Officers meeting agenda, 3 Dec 1971 (Box 47, Folder 2)
      - Report, newsletter, meeting, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 4)
      - 4th annual meeting, Apr 1972 (Box 47, Folder 5)
      - Meetings, 1972 (Box 47, Folder 6)
      - 5th annual meeting, Apr 1973 (Box 47, Folder 7)
      - 15th annual meeting, Apr 1983 (Box 47, Folder 8)
      - Meetings, 1988, 1992-2003 (Box 47, Folder 9-31)
      - Meetings, 2005-10 (Box 48, Folder 1-25)
      - Meetings, 2010-11 (Box 49, Folder 1-17)
    - Annual meeting minutes, Apr 2000-05 (Box 49, Folder 18-23)
    - Executive Committee minutes, 2000-11 (Box 49, Folder 24-34)
    - Officer and committee conveners reports
      - 2000-02 (Box 49, Folder 35-39)
      - 2002-07 (Box 50, Folder 1-8)
    - Information sheet on granting patterns of VGIF, 1970-2003 (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Florine Swanson, 2000 (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors
      - Minutes, 2000-02 (Box 50, Folder 11-14)
      - Handbook, 2002 (Box 50, Folder 15)
      - Minutes, 2003-08 (Box 50, Folder 16-21)
      - Orientation packet, 2009 (Box 50, Folder 22-23)
      - Minutes, 2010-11 (Box 50, Folder 24-29)
    - Officers
      - Treasurer
        - Treasurer's report, financial statement, Dec 1993 (Box 51, Folder 1)
        - Financial statement, 1998 (Box 51, Folder 2)
        - Employer's Guide to Tax, 2001 (Box 51, Folder 3)
        - Membership dues and donations, 2002 (Box 51, Folder 4-20)
        - Investment portfolios
          - 2002 (Box 51, Folder 21-22)
          - 2002-08 (Box 52, Folder 1-6)
        - Citicorp checking account, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 7-9)
        - Payroll, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 10-12)
        - Expenses, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 13-15)
        - Petty cash/credit card, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 16-17)
        - Financial correspondence, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 18)
        - Tax forms, estates, and bequests, 2002-07 (Box 52, Folder 19-20)
        - Certificate of incorporation, 2010 (Box 52, Folder 21)
        - Marble Collegiate lease, 2002-07 (Box 52, Folder 22-23)
        - Liability insurance, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 24)
      - President
        - Althea Hottel, 1970-71 (Box 53, Folder 1-2)
        - Virginia Maynard, Mar-Aug 1972 (Box 53, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence
          - 1983-84 (Box 53, Folder 4)
          - 1999-2001 (Box 53, Folder 5)
        - Appointments to committees, 2001 (Box 53, Folder 6)
        - Sema Faigen, 2000-02 (Box 53, Folder 7)
        - Response to attacks of Sep 11, 2001 (Box 53, Folder 8)
        - Transition: Sema Faigen and Barbara Carey, 2002 (Box 53, Folder 9)
        - Barbara Carey
          - International members, 2002-05 (Box 53, Folder 10)
          - Condolence letters (Box 53, Folder 11)
          - Correspondence, 2002-04 (Box 53, Folder 12-14)
          - Donation thank-you notes, Palmer gift (Box 53, Folder 15)
          - Archives, 2 Oct 2003 (Box 53, Folder 16)
          - Photographs, ca. 2003 (Box 53, Folder 17)
          - News article, photographs, personal correspondence, awards, and resume (Box 53, Folder 18)
          - President's Report, 2004 (Box 53, Folder 19)
        - News article: Sema Faigen (Box 53, Folder 20)
    - Publications
      - VGIF brochures (Box 53, Folder 21)
        [see also: oversize materials]
      - "VG Update," Jan 2000-Feb 2013 (Box 53, Folder 22-23)
      - "The Flash," Feb 2005-Mar 2013 (Box 53, Folder 24)
    - Leaders, 1978-2005 and 1969-2006; Jan 2003 Committee membership (Box 53, Folder 25)
    - Letterhead, blank certificates, ca. 2002-08 (Box 53, Folder 26)
    - Virginia Gildersleeve biographical materials
      - Nomination to National Women's Hall of Fame (Box 53, Folder 27)
      - Research on Gildersleeve letter re: Nuremberg Trials, 2005 (Box 53, Folder 28)
      - Writings and biographical information, photograph and slide (Box 53, Folder 29)
    - News Articles General Non-Profit (Box 53, Folder 30)
    - Partner or potential partner organizations
      - General, 2002-07, undated (Box 54, Folder 1)
      - Foundations directory, 1973 (Box 54, Folder 2)
      - United Nations
        - San Francisco conference programs, 1945 (Box 54, Folder 3)
        - Nairobi conference, 1985 (Box 54, Folder 4)
        - Development Fund for Women, 1985 (Box 54, Folder 5)
        - Application for UN consultative status, 2003 (Box 54, Folder 6)
        - NGO accreditation, 2005 (Box 54, Folder 7)
        - UNIFEM "Progress of the World's Women" - Millenium development goals, 2002 (Box 54, Folder 8)
        - Commission on the Status of Women handbook, Mar 2004 (Box 54, Folder 9)
        - Women's UN Report Network, 2005-06 (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - California Women's Agenda, 2003 (includes statement condemning US invasion of Iraq) (Box 54, Folder 11)
      - VG Australia, 1994-2001 (Box 54, Folder 12)
      - Australian Federation of University Women
        - 1982-84 (Box 54, Folder 13)
        - 2004 (Box 54, Folder 14)
        - "Graduate Women," 2005-06 (Box 54, Folder 15)
      - New Zealand Federation of Graduate Women, circa 2000-10 (Box 54, Folder 16)
      - Sri Lankan Journal for Women's Liberation, May 2006 (Box 54, Folder 17)
      - University Women of Europe, 2005-06 (Box 54, Folder 18-20)
      - Canadian Federation of University Women (Box 54)
        - Annual meetings, 2003-05 (Box 54, Folder 21-22)
        - Directories, 2002-06 (Box 54, Folder 23-26)
      - American Association of University Women, 1997-2007 (Box 55, Folder 1-6)
      - International Federation of University Women (IFUW)
        - Ottawa Conference, 2001 (Box 55, Folder 7)
        - Perth Conference, 2004 (Box 55, Folder 8-9)
        - Manchester Conference, 2007 (Box 55, Folder 10-12)
      - "Balkan Women: Reality and Perspectives:" Albanian Association of Graduate Women, Sep 2004 (Box 55, Folder 13)
      - AIDS Statement at World Alliance for Breastfeeding (WABA) Conference, 2002 (Box 55, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. COMMITTEES
  - PART I.
    - Lists of committee members, 1973-76, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Agendas and minutes of joint committee meetings, 1972, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Members' annual meeting attendance records, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Awards, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1975-78 (Box 12, Folder 5-8)